Guide to the Marcel Kurpershoek papers AD.MC.054
New York University Abu Dhabi Library
Marcel Kurpershoek papers
1970-2017
New York University Abu Dhabi Library
Kurpershoek, Marcel
AD.MC.054
8.5 Linear Feet in 20 boxes, circa 120 books, and circa 12 - 15 framed photographs.
Manuscript drafts, transcripts, field notes, correspondence, speeches, publications and research materials, chiefly related to the research and writings of P. Marcel Kurpershoek, in particular his work on oral poetry traditions of Bedouin tribes of central Saudi Arabia. Also includes materials related to other writings by Kurpershoek, including manuscript drafts and research materials for his doctoral dissertation on the Egyptian writer, Yusuf Idris.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for use in the Archives and Special Collections Reading Room, New York University Abu Dhabi Library.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by P. Marcel Kurpershoek, 2018.
Arrangement
The Marcel Kurpershoek collection is arranged in seven series: I. Publications, II. Correspondence, speeches and miscellaneous writings, III. Research notes and background materials, IV. Dissertation and other academic materials, V. Printed materials, VI. Photographs and other miscellanea, VII. Film footage. The series are arranged largely in alphabetical order by folder title, with some sub-series added in the "Publications" series for materials related to individual published works.
Biographical statement
Paul Marcel Kurpershoek was born in The Hague, the Netherlands, in 1949. After completing his secondary schooling (Gymnasium) in 1967, he attended the University of Leiden for his undergraduate degree, studying Arabic literature, completing his studies there in 1970, following which he spent a year of further study in Cairo. In 1975, he joined the diplomatic service of the Foreign Ministry of the Netherlands, and during the next several decades, served in postings in Egypt, Syria, Saudi Arabia, among other locations, and later served as the Ambassador to Pakistan, Afghanistan, Turkey, and Poland, and as a Dutch special representative for Syria, based in Istanbul.
During his diplomatic career, he also pursued a scholarly one, completing a doctorate in Arabic literature from the University of Leiden in 1980, with a dissertation about the Egyptian short story writer Yusuf Idris, subsequently published as "The short stories of Yūsuf Idrīs: a modern Egyptian author" (Leiden: Brill, 1981). During his posting in Riyadh in the late 1980s, his interest in the oral poetic traditions of Bedouin tribes of central Saudi Arabia led him to take a sabbatical year between postings in 1989 to conduct field work in Nejd and Wadi Dawasir, recording and transcribing such poetry, also known as Nabati poetry. The resulting work led to the publication of five scholarly volumes of such poetry, with transcriptions, translations, and scholarly analyses, titled "Oral Poetry and Narratives of Central Arabia" (Leiden: Brill, 1994-2005).
He also authored several several titles about his field work in Arabia for a popular audience, including "Diep in Arabië" (Amsterdam: Meulenhoff, 1992), "De laatste Bedoeïen"(Amsterdam: Meulenhoff, 1995), and an English translation and adaptation of those two titles, "Arabia of the Bedouins" (London: Saqi Books, 2001), as well an Arabic translation of the latter title, "al-Badawī al-akhīr: al-qabāʼil al-badawīyah fī al-ṣaḥrāʼ al-ʻArabīyah" (London / Beirut: Saqi Books, 2002), among other books, essays, and journal articles. His interest in the wider Middle East also led him to publish a book about the history of various claims to Jerusalem "Onzalig Jeruzalem" (Amsterdam: Meulenhoff, 1996).
After his retirement from diplomatic service, Kurpershoek continued his scholarly work on Arabic literature and Nabati poetry, joining New York University Abu Dhabi as a Senior Research Fellow in the Humanities Research Fellowship Program, and has published further works through the university's Library of Arabic Literature series, including "Arabian Satire: Poetry from 18th century Najd" (New York: NYU Press, 2017). In addition, his fieldwork in Saudi Arabia was profiled in a television documentary on the al Arabiya network in 2017 and 2018 titled "The Last Traveller."
Content Description
Manuscript drafts, transcripts, field notes, correspondence, speeches, publications and research materials, chiefly related to the research and writings of P. Marcel Kurpershoek, in particular his work on oral poetry traditions of Bedouin tribes of central Saudi Arabia. Also includes materials related to other writings by Kurpershoek, including manuscript drafts and research materials for his doctoral dissertation on the Egyptian writer, Yusuf Idris.
The collection is divided into seven series. The "Publications" series contains manuscript and typescript drafts, notes, and other materials used or created by Kurpershoek in the writing and editing of several of his books, including the "Oral Poetry and Narratives of Central Arabia," his chief scholarly work on Nabati poetry. The materials related to that often demonstrate his process of recording, transcribing, and translating poetry that Bedouins recited to him during his field work in Saudi Arabia, and often include notebooks in which he first transcribed these poems from audio recordings he had made, and then subsequent drafts in Arabic, with edits and corrections provided by the poets or those close to them, or from other scholars he worked with, primarily Saad Sowayyan, a Saudi scholar of Nabati poetry.
The "Correspondence, speeches and other writings" groups together a smaller amount of material, ranging from speeches or brief articles compiled by Kurpershoek about Nabati poetry and his field work in Saudi Arabia, to copies of correspondence he sent to his wife, Betsy Udink, during his trips to Nejd or elsewhere in Saudi Arabia, in which he describes his experiences and field work. The "Research notes and background materials" contains chiefly notes compiled by Kurpershoek from secondary sources, and "Printed materials" contain copies of books or other difficult to obtain published materials related to Nabati poetry, and used by Kurpershoek in his research.
The series "Dissertation and other academic materials" relates primarily to Kurpershoek's research and writing of his dissertation on the Egyptian writer Yusuf Idris, including transcripts of interviews Kurpershoek conducted with Idris, news clippings from the Egyptian press about Idris, drafts of Kurpershoek's dissertation text, and a Dutch translation by Kurpershoek of one of Idris's short stories, "al Haram." Also included are notes retained by Kurpershoek during an earlier study visit to Cairo in 1970, and materials related to the granting of his doctorate at the University of Leiden in 1980.
A small amount of photographs are included in the "Photographs" series, chiefly those taken by Kurpershoek during his field visits in Saudi Arabia, and enlarged as poster-sized reproductions. The series "Film Footage" contains raw footage created by staff with Middle East News and the Al Arabiya television network, for use in a documentary film about Kurpershoek titled "The Last Traveler" in 2017. The film is still in process at the time of the creation of this finding aid, but shows Kurpershoek visiting, interviewing, and holding discussions with a number of Saudi Bedouin poets, among other materials utilized in the documentary, and is under license to Middle East News.
Dialect poetry, Arabic--Saudi Arabia--Najd.; Arabic poetry--Saudi Arabia.; Najd, Saudi Arabia; Dawāsir Wadi, Saudi Arabia; Idrīs, Yūsuf--Criticism and interpretation.
- Publications, circa 1988-2005
  - Oral Poetry and Narratives from Central Arabia: Volume 1: The Poetry of ad-Dindan
    - Glossary, manuscript (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Glossary, typescript (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Manuscript draft (preface and introduction) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Notes on transcribed texts of poetry (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Transcriptions of poetry (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Typescript text of volume, with edits (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Oral Poetry and Narratives from Central Arabia: Volume 2: The Story of a Desert Knight
    - Glossary—manuscript (1) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Glossary—manuscript (2) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Glossary—typescript, with edits by Saad Sowayan (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript draft of text, "Khaled I" (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Manuscript draft of text, "Khaled II" (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Metrical studies (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Notes (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Place names (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Poetry, transcripts of (Latin script) (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Poetry, transcripts of (Arabic script), initial transcripts in "Record Book" (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Poetry, transcripts of, (Arabic script), with annotations and edits made in field, from poets and transmitters. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Text, manuscript draft, "Language and Prosody" (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Text, manuscript draft, "Variant Readings of Poems" (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Text, typescript draft, with edits by Saad Sowayan (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Oral Poetry and Narratives from Central Arabia: Volume 3:. Bedouin Poets of the Dawasir Tribe
    - Notes and questions (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Poetry: Bkheitan: photocopy of transcribed poems written down by Bkheitan (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Poetry: Bkheitan: transcripts with edits (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Poetry: ad-Dindan: transcripts (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Poetry: Ibn Batla: translations (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Poetry: Ibn Batla: transcripts (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Poetry: transcripts, general (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Oral Poetry and Narratives from Central Arabia: Volume 4:. A Saudi Tribal History, 1995-2002, and undated
    - Correspondence: Bearman, Peri, 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence: Editorial, general, 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence: Gelder, Geert van, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence: Sowayan, Saad, 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Notes: general (1) (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Notes: general (2) (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Notes: historical and background (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Notes: "Muslihah," or "peace poem" (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Notes: topical (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Poetry: transcripts, fragments (manuscript) (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Poetry: transcripts, general, arranged by location on tape recordings (1) (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Poetry: transcripts, general, arranged by location on tape recordings (2) (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Poetry: transcripts, Arabic script ("Record Book") (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Poetry: transcripts (from red binder, Arabic script): general (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Poetry: transcripts (from red binder, Arabic script): Bkhitan (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Poetry: transcripts (from red binder, Arabic script): Nadir al Nahish (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Poetry: transcripts (from red binder, Arabic script): Saied ibn Muriti (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Poetry: transcripts (from red binder, Arabic script): Mitib (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Poetry: transcripts (from red binder, Arabic script): Farruj (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Poetry: transcripts (from red binder, Arabic script): Saqr (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Poetry: transcripts (from red binder, Arabic script): Fahed ibn Reyn (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Poetry: transcripts (from red binder, Arabic script): Dindan (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Poetry: transcripts (from red binder, Arabic script): Ibn Nuwayyiz (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Poetry: transcripts: al-Nahish and Ibn Husn (Latin script) (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Poetry: transcripts: al-Nahish: typescript (Arabic script) with edits and annotations by Majid al Nahish, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Poetry: Bkheitan: transcripts, manuscript (Latin script), February 1999 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Travel plans for field work, 1996-1998 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Typescript text, with edits (1) (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Typescript text, with edits (2) (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Oral Poetry and Narratives from Central Arabia: unidentified materials
    - Poetry transcripts: manuscript (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Poetry transcripts: typescript (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Other writings: Diep in Arabië, De laatste Bedoeïen, Onzalige Jerusalem
    - Diep in Arabië: outline (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Diep in Arabië: manuscript draft (1) (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Diep in Arabië: manuscript draft (2) (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Diep in Arabië: manuscript draft (3) (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Diep in Arabië: manuscript draft (4) (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Diep in Arabië: manuscript draft (5) (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Diep in Arabië: poetry: poem about coffee, Dubais al Alabi (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Diep in Arabië: poetry: Gana (Qana) (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Diep in Arabië: promotion (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Diep in Arabië: typescript draft (1) (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Diep in Arabië: typescript draft (2) (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Diep in Arabië: typescript draft (3) (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Diep in Arabië: typescript draft: sent to mother for review (1) (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Diep in Arabië: typescript draft: sent to mother for review (2) (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - De laatste Bedoeïen: manuscript draft (1) (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - De laatste Bedoeïen: manuscript draft (2) (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Onzalige Jerusalem: background materials (1) (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Onzalige Jerusalem: background materials (2) (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Onzalige Jerusalem: manuscript draft (1) (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Onzalige Jerusalem: manuscript draft (2) (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Onzalige Jerusalem: manuscript draft (3) (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Onzalige Jerusalem: manuscript draft (4) (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Onzalige Jerusalem: manuscript draft (5) (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Onzalige Jerusalem: manuscript draft, fragments (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Onzalige Jerusalem: notes (1) (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Onzalige Jerusalem: notes (2) (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Onzalige Jerusalem: photographs, negatives (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, speeches, and miscellaneous writings, 1988-2000
  - Correspondence: Udink, Betsy: letters sent to her by PMK from Saudi Arabia, during fieldwork, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Research trips, planning and logistics, 1989-1994 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Research trips, planning and logistics, 1996-1998 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Readings of Bedouin poetry: Arabic texts (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Readings of Bedouin poetry: Dutch translations and notes (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Land Rover Club of Saudi Arabia, "The Sand Ladder:" submissions for newsletter, 1988-1989 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Land Rover Club of Saudi Arabia, "The Sand Ladder," articles translated into Arabic, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Lecture given in Abu Dhabi, unidentified venue, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Speeches: "'Wie Luidt de Doodsklok over de Arabieren?': Arabisme, Islam, en de Wereldbank."[speech given at the University of Leiden], September 18, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Writings: "Heartbeat: Conventionality and Originality in Najd Poetry," Asian Folklore Studies, vol. 52, pp. 33-74, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Writings: "Between ad-Dakhul and 'Afif: Oral Traditions of the 'Utaybah Tribe in Central Najd," Zeitschrift für arabische Linguistik, vol. 26, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Writings: "Poetry and Tribal Identity," in Proceedings of an International Conference on Middle Eastern Popular Culture, Magdalen College, Oxford, 17-21 September 2000 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Research notes and background materials, 1984-2007, and undated
  - Bibliography of popular (Nabati) poetry (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Calendar (from time of field work in Saudi Arabia), 1989 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Nejd, general (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Netherlands, Consulate at Jeddah: copies of archival documents from 1926-1948 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - News clipping: about Kurpershoek lecture in Abu Dhabi (al-Ittihad), 2002 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Notes: exercises in translation and transliteration, from classical Arabic into Bedouin dialect (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Notes: topics, general (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Notes: themes in Bedouin poetry: plants and camels (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Notes: themes in Bedouin poetry: stars (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Notes: themes in Bedouin poetry: horses, palm trees, tents (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Notes: Arabic terms, drawn from other sources (Doughty, Hess, Musil), folder 1 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Notes: Arabic terms, drawn from other sources (Doughty, Hess, Musil), folder 2 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Notes: Arabic terms, drawn from other sources (Doughty, Hess, Musil), folder 3 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Poetry: Ibn Sbayyil: Library of Arabic Literature publication project, "Arabian Romantic". Poems recorded in KSA from Adbullah Nafish and transcribed by PMK (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Poetry: Shammar (1): photocopy of printed text, with handwritten annotations, after consultation with Shammar poets. (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Poetry: Shammar (2): correspondence, photocopies of texts of transcriptions (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Poetry: Shammar (3): collected during research visit, not used in publication (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Photographs, copies of images from Snouck Hurgronje (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Project outline, for Saudi officials (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Qusaybi, Ghani al-: open letter/poem to King, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Shammar descendants in Turkey (Ahmed Sammaroglu): DVD of visit, 2007 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Shammar descendants in Turkey (Ahmed Sammaroglu): CDs of spoken poetry, recorded during Kurpershoek visit, 2007 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Ship's journal: from journey in Arabian Gulf, with copy of original text, English and Arabic translations, and notes. Copied from Dutch archive (unidentified, likely National Archives, The Hague). Tido Fredrik Van Kniphausen (captain) (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Sources (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Trip notes: Sinai, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Trip notes: Hail, May 1988 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Trip notes: Hail, July 1988 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Trip notes: Empty Quarter, February 1989 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Trip notes: Nifi, July 1989 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Wadi Dawasir: Background (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Wadi Dawasir: News clippings (1) (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Wadi Dawasir: News clippings (2) (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Wadi Dawasir: question of true Sheikh of Dawasir (Box 9, Folder 16)
- Dissertation and other academic materials, University of Leiden, 1970-1995
  - Bibliographies on Yusuf Idris and works (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Biography of Yusuf Idris: typescript (copy) (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Dissertation: manuscript draft of text (1) (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Dissertation: manuscript draft of text (2) (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Dissertation: manuscript draft of text (3) (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Dissertation: manuscript draft of text (4) (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Dissertation: typescript draft segment (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Dissertation: Typescript draft, with corrections by Rowland Ellis (1) (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Dissertation: Typescript draft, with corrections by Rowland Ellis (2) (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Dissertation: Typescript draft, with corrections by Rowland Ellis (3) (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Dissertation: Typescript draft, with corrections by Rowland Ellis (4) (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Dissertation: Typescript draft, September 1980 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Dissertation: footnotes (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Dissertation: corrections to text (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Dissertation text: proofs of published version, July 1980 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Dissertation text: proofs of published version, October 1980 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Dissertation: interviews by PMK with Yusuf Idris: notes and partial transcript, 1976-1978 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Dissertation: interviews by PMK with Yusuf Idris: notes and questions, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Dissertation: interviews by PMK with Yusuf Idris: summaries (Dutch) (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Dissertation: interviews by PMK with Yusuf Idris: transcripts (Arabic), 1978 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Dissertation: news clippings by and about Y. Idris (1), 1976-1995 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Dissertation: news clippings by and about Y. Idris (2), 1976-1995 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Dissertation: news clippings by and about Y. Idris (3), 1976-1995 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Dissertation: news clippings by and about Y. Idris (4), 1976-1995 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Dissertation: news clippings by and about Y. Idris (5), 1976-1995 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Dissertation: notes, on notecards (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Dissertation: notes, general (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Dissertation: notes, as removed from binder (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Dissertation: notes, interviews of Y. Idris by others (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Dissertation: notes, from review of Egyptian newspapers in Dar al Kutub (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Dissertation: notes, from various sources (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Dissertation: quotations, selected (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Other: notes, Cairo (Mu'ayyad Sheikh al Yusuf), 1970-1971 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Other: notes, Cairo, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Other: promotion to doctorate, University of Leiden, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Other: Dutch translation of "al Haram" by Yusuf Idris, by P. Kurpershoek (1) (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Other: Dutch translation of "al Haram" by Yusuf Idris, by P. Kurpershoek (2) (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Printed material: copied books and texts in Arabic and English
  - Awwal khultah min al shehr al qaltah [first collection of Nabati poetry ever Published, poetry duels]. Ali al Abdulrahman abu Majid, and Ali al Salem al 'Abbad. [undated] (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Abdulrahman ibn Nasir. Anwan al Sa'd wa al Majd. [Resumes of the history of Saudi Arabia before the coming of the late Ibn Saud and his first half of His reign after the year 1936…] Folder 1 [undated] (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Abdulrahman ibn Nasir. Anwan al Sa'd wa al Majd. [Resumes of the history of Saudi Arabia before the coming of the late Ibn Saud and his first half of His reign after the year 1936…] Folder 2 [undated] (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Abu Hakima, Ahmad (editor). Lamʿ al Shihāb (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Aṣmaʿī, al-. Kitāb al-Nabāt [book of plants]. Originally from AH 216, Cairo. Later edition of classic, 1972. Edited by Abdullah Yusuf al Ghunaym. (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Azzawi, Abbas al. Tribes of Iraq, Baghdad, vol. 1, pt. 1, 1937 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Azzawi, Abbas al. Tribes of Iraq, Baghdad, vol. 1, pt. 2, 1937 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Azzawi, Abbas al. Tribes of Iraq: the Kurds, Baghdad, vol. 2, 1947 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Azzawi, Abbas al. Tribes of Iraq: the settled areas, Baghdad, vol. 3, 1956 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Azzawi, Abbas al. Tribes of Iraq: the settled areas, Baghdad, vol. 4, 1956 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Bilaid. 'Atiq ibn Ghayth al Bilādī. Genealogy of Ḥarb tribe. Dar Mekka, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Batnuni [?], Mohammed Labib al. al Rihlat al hejaziya. [Journey to Hejaz]. AH 1329, Cairo. (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Faqhari, Mohamed ibn Umar al. Akhbar al-Najdiyyah [report on Nejd]. (Riyadh, ….). Edited by Abdullah ibn Yusuf al Shibl. (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Muhammed, Fahad. Diwan ibn Firdaws [book of poetry] (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Hambali. Sheikh Ibrahim ibn Saleh ibn Issa al Nejdi al.. Kitab [Book of the string of pearls in what concerns events in Nejd in the latter part of the 13th century and the first part of the 14th century). (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Ta'rīkh Ḥamad ibn Muḥammed ibn Laʿbūn. (Printed in Mecca, i.e., Umm al Qura) (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Hamza, Fuad. Heart of the Arabian Peninsula. [quite important] Qalb al Jazirat al 'Arab. Volume 1, 1933 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Hamza, Fuad. Heart of the Arabian Peninsula. [quite important] Qalb al Jazirat al 'Arab. Volume 2, 1933 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Hamza, Fuad. Heart of the Arabian Peninsula. [quite important] Qalb al Jazirat al 'Arab. Volume 3, 1933 (Box 15, Folder 6)